Nanking Incident Collection
Nanking Incident Collection
1927-1929, undated
1 folder, approx. 20 items (SC)
Collection of letters, statements, clippings relating to the March 1927 invasion of the city by the Kuomintang (Chinese Nationalist) troops.
2580665
Biographical History
The Nanking Incident occurred on March 21-23, 1927 when Kuomintang (Chinese Nationalist) troops entered the city as part of their Northern Expedition military campaign (1926-1928). Troops particularly targeted the city's foreign residents; several were killed or injured and their property looted, and the American, Japanese and British consulates were attacked. Western and Japanese warships on the river responded by shelling Chinese forces in an effort to stop the looting of the city. The Nationalist Government blamed "communists and their evil influences" for the disturbance.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Nanking Incident Collection consists of clippings, statements, and letters. Authors of the items include private citizens as well as the University of Nanking, the China Christian Educational Association, the acting president of Central China University, and Canton Union Theological College.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Pryor, Helen (Brenton) 1897-; Brown, Fred R., 1888-1966.; China Christian Educational Association.; Communism -- China.; Zhongguo guo min dang.; China -- History -- Military; Nanjing (Jiangsu Sheng, China) -- History; Clippings (information artifacts); Letters (correspondence); Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Descriptions of the Nanking incident
  - Newsclipping, Shanghai Times, 25 April 1927 (Sc 203)
  - Statement by Helen Brenton Pryor, typescript carbon, 7 pp. (Sc 203)
  - Statement by Dr. Harry F. Rowe, typescript, 2 pp. (Sc 203)
  - Statement by R.J. Pryor, typescript, 8 pp. (Sc 203)
  - Statement by Dr. Brown, printed, 5 pp. (Sc 203)
  - Statement by Miss Golisch, printed, 6 pp. (Sc 203)
- Correspondence and reports
  - University of Nanking
    - John H. Reisner, 1927-1928; letters no. 6-11, printed; discusses military and political situations, conditions on campus, soldiers in the buildings, budget, repairs, etc.; 66 pp. (Sc 203)
    - A.J. Bowen (Reisner's successor), October 1928-April 1929; continuation of above letters, printed; 13 pp. (Sc 203)
  - China Christian Educational Association, Shanghai
    - Printed material
      - "A statement to Chinese friends," by a group of Nanking missionaries, April 21, 1927; 4 pp. (Sc 203)
      - "Christian education in Nanchang," by Fred R. Brown, 3 pp. (Sc 203)
    - Correspondence and reports
      - Sanford C. C. Chen, letter "Dear Friend...", May 2, 1927; lists and describes following reports (Sc 203)
      - no. 348 Christian schools under the Nationalist government, 4 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 349 letter from acting president of Central China University, 3 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 355 Christian schools under the Nationalist government, by E. W. Wallace, report of visit to Wuhan; 14 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 367 Inter-Provincial Conference of the English Baptist Mission, 2 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 369 Extract from a letter by Mrs. J.R. Lingle, Fuh Siang Girls' School, Changsha, 2 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 371 Canton Union Theological College, 1 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 372 Conference with Dr. W.H. Kilpatrick, 3 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 374 H.C. Tsao, report of visit to Wuhan; 11 pp. (Sc 203)
      - no. 375 Conference of Missionary Educators, Shanghai, 7 pp. (Sc 203)
      - Duplicate set of above letters and reports (Sc 203)